=5 Structural Bioinformatics=
==5.9 Homology Modelling==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 3 h; taken 4 h; date started: 2019-11-28; date completed: 2019-11-29

[[User:Zhi Wei Zeng|Zhi Wei Zeng]] ([[User talk:Zhi Wei Zeng|talk]]) 23:25, 29 November 2019 (EST)
</div>

;Motivation:
Protein structure prediction/inference from known structures of homologues

Once we know there is homology, it is basically certain that the structures are similar, even if sequences have diverged a lot (to a value lower than non-homologous sequences is entirely possible)

;Specific actions:
Align target sequence with sequence of a suitable structure template > Replace coordinates of residues in the template structure with the ones in the target sequence

;Indels:
:* Cannot be modelled with certainty at all.
:* Often in loops. When they are not, there are usually extra structurally accommodating features
:* Uniform gap penalties are not biological. Use structure-weighted gap penalties if available

;Accuracy of homology modelling is determined by sequence alignment accuracy:
:* Correct sequence alignment is the most important factor
:* Errors resulted from alignment typically cannot be fixed after model construction
:* Make sure to use the best MSA. Include many homologues to resolve ambiguities if possible
:* Manual edit alignments if necessary

;Choice of template:
Highest sequence similarity, close-to-native structures, best resolution possible

Residue correlations derived from structural alignment can be different from that derived from optimal sequence alignment.

;Quality assessment of models:
Occupancy values in PDB file, "reliability metrics", unreliable disordered regions and indels and solvent accessible regions

'''''Bottom line -- Do not interpret from aspects for which the homology model does not provide information'''''

Seems like energy minimization often does not improve homology models..

;Online servers for homology modelling:
:* SWISS-MODEL: also a database of homology models

===5.9.1 Construct homology model for ERECY Mbp1===
;Objectives:
:* Construct a molecular model of APSES domain of ERECY_Mbp1
:* Hopefully construct conservation patterns of key residues with their potential to bind DNA

;Target Sequence
Retrieve MYSPE APSES domain ''target sequence''. The source code is [http://steipe.biochemistry.utoronto.ca/abc/index.php/BIN-SX-Homology_modelling#Target_sequence here]

Need to <code>init()</code> the ABC-units R-project and replace <code>source("makeProteinDB.R")</code> with:

<source lang="R">
library(jsonlite)
source("../makeProteinDB.R")
</source>

<code>targetSeq</code> returns the following:
 MBP1_ERECY 
 "QIYSAKYSGVEVYEFIHPTGSIMKRKADDWVNATHILKAAKFAKAKRTRILEKEVIKDIHEKVQGGFGKYQGTWVPLDIARRLAEKFDVLEELRPLFDF"

;Choice of Template

Find PDB coordinate set that has sufficient sequence similarity to the target.

A lot of biological and biochemical considerations weigh in during selection of suitable template structure.

[http://steipe.biochemistry.utoronto.ca/abc/index.php/Template_choice_principles More guides on selecting template]

;Activity 1 - Find a template through PDB advanced searching

1. Go to https://www.rcsb.org/

2. Go to advanced search

3. "Choose a Query Type" as "Sequence (BLAST/PSI-BLAST)"

4. Use the sequence above loaded from my R-project. Use "BLAST" as "Search Tool". "No" to "Mask Low Complexity". Everything else default

5. "Submit Query"

6. Report of search results:

[[File:pdb_report.jpg|500px]]

 1BM8: Excellent resolution of 1.7 A. E-value is 7.52638E-45. No gap. 84% identity and 94% similarity.

 1L3G: Solution NMR ensemble. Typically not suitable.

 1MB1: Also Mbp1 from Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Lower resolution than 1BM8 (2.1 A, still pretty good)

 4UX5: Resolution 2.4 A. Complexed with DNA. From Candida albicans, Magnaporthe oryzae?. E-value is 1.16655E-29. 60% identity and 76% similarity. There is one gap.

 4WUV: Highest resolution, but least related and most distant.

7. Download FASTA sequence files for 1BM8 and 4UX5. Keep only the Chain A for 4UX5. This results in two saved files of "1BM8_A.fa" and "4UX5_A.fa".

;Activity 2 - Create input alignment

The R-code for this activity is generously provided [http://steipe.biochemistry.utoronto.ca/abc/index.php/BIN-SX-Homology_modelling#The_input_alignment here].

This source code allows retrieval of protein sequences in myDB that are Mbp1. Adding to the set also the sequences read from "1BM8_A.fa" and "4UX5_A.fa".

Then, multiple sequence alignment with all these sequences are calculated.

Saved console print-out of alignment results in "4UX5.aln" and "1BM8.aln".

<span style="color:green">'''Decided on 1BM8 as the template and continue following the source code with this info.'''</span>

<span style="color:green">'''The input sequence alignment for homology modelling in FASTA format is obtained from console print-out and saved as "hm.mfa"'''</span>

;Activity 3 - Create a homology model with SWISS-MODEL

1. Go to https://swissmodel.expasy.org/ and "Start Modelling"

2. Choose "Target-Template Alignment". Copy and paste contents from "hm.mfa" into the query field. Then, "Build Model".

3. The job report is at https://swissmodel.expasy.org/interactive/5XQ5Az/models/report.html

The model looks very good. With few faint red regions at loopy regions. QMEAN is -0.37

;Modelling process documentation is [https://swissmodel.expasy.org/docs/help here]

:* GMQE: template-target alignment, method of searching template, target coverage > measure of accuracy of model
:* QMEAN: "degree of nativeness". How good the agreement of structure would be with experimental ones of similar size.

4. Download the Model_01 as PDB file "MBP1_ERECY-APSES.pdb".

<span style="color:red">The residue numbering of PDB file needs fixing. It was renumbered. e.g. the first residue 1 should be 11 (GLN11).</span>

;Activity 4 - Renumbering the PDB file of the model generated with bio3d package

The source code is generously provided [http://steipe.biochemistry.utoronto.ca/abc/index.php/BIN-SX-Homology_modelling#Renumbering_the_model here]. 

Useful functions:
:* bio3d::read.pdb()

* Need to change all lines with "MYSPE" string to "ERECY"
* Need to properly specify paths to the files. For me they are stored in "BCH1441" and not "BCH1441/ABC-units"

The last line should actually be:
<code>bio3d::write.pdb(pdb = MYSPEmodel, file=PDB_OUTFILE)</code>

'''Looking at the result, I guess we are numbering the residues according to Saccharomyces cerevisiae Mbp1 numbering.'''

;Activity 5 - Visualization

The PDB output from SWISS-MODEL has a quality scores based on energies from molecular mechanics in the B-factor column.

1. Open "MBP1_ERECY-APSESrenum.pdb" in Chimera.

2. Use "bfactor" as attribute for "Attributes of Atoms". Render.

[[File:bfactor_col.jpg|500px]]

The core has better energies, probably because more residues around providing favourable interactions.

Importantly, the residues on the surface would be solvent accessible and expected to be flexible. Thus the structural certainty here is low.

<span style="color:green">bio3d has tools that customize values to be placed in b-factor for customizable colouring during rendering</span>

;Activity 6 - Modelling DNA binding for ERECY_Mbp1 based on a homologous protein structure bound to DNA

1. In Chimera, <code>open 4ux5</code>

2. Make a copy of the homology model with "copy/combine" in the "Model Panel"

3. In "MatchMaker" panel, I did not see a radio button. But I am able to select individual chain for a model by choosing "Specific chain in reference structure with best-aligning chain in match structure".

4. Match one homology model to chain A of 4ux5. Match the copy of homology model to chain B.

5. Render in such way that residues are coloured according to "AL2CO" conservation style . Bright red is not well-conserved, whereas grey is highly conserved:

<span style="color:red">(Instructions given is not clear, so I had to load "hm.mfa" to get "Multalign Viewer" to even do anything)</span>

[[File:conserved.jpg|500px]]

Selected protein residues that are within 5 A of nucleic acids results in the following selection:

[[File:5na.jpg|500px]]

* They are very well conserved. They are limited within residues 9-12,37,41,46-52,54-55,59,65,67-72,74-76.

* These residues are identical except at residues 9 (K-R) and 59 (I-L). Still very similar

Conservation within the family should look at the file "APSES-MBP1.fa" with e.g. JalView (I do not have it yet)


==5.8 Structural Superposition==
;Motivation:
Structural alignment, conserved interaction etc. Reveal alignments between poorly conserved sequence identities

;Criteria:
Minimized RMSD after translation+rotation

;Complications:
Choice of coordinate subsets (does not always make sense to align all coordinates. e.g. domains? relatively immobile elements?)

;Superposition servers:
:* VAST (Vector Alignment Search Tool): find similar structures by similarly oriented and arranged elements of secondary structures
:* DALI: collections of superimposed domains?

;Notes from working with [https://www.cgl.ucsf.edu/chimera/docs/UsersGuide/tutorials/alignments.html Chimera Superpositions and Alignments Tutorial]

Key tools for structural alignment:
MatchMaker, Match -> Align, Multalign Viewer

'''''{{WP|Circular permutation in proteins|Circular permutation}} of protein sequence is a thing?!'''''

;Bio3d tutorials:
:* [http://thegrantlab.org/bio3d/tutorials/structure-analysis Structural analysis]
:* [http://thegrantlab.org/bio3d/tutorials/principal-component-analysis PCA]


==5.7 Protein Structural Domains==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 2 h; taken 2.5 h; date started: 2019-10-30; date completed: 2019-10-31

[[User:Zhi Wei Zeng|Zhi Wei Zeng]] ([[User talk:Zhi Wei Zeng|talk]]) 23:45, 31 October 2019 (EDT)
</div>

;Domains:
Compact, somewhat independent, efficient folding, modular protein organization
:* ''Often'' domains have distinct functions
:* Useful for identifying folding units, understanding evolutionary history, predicting protein function, classifying proteins

;Larger proteins tend to have more than 1 domains.
:* Sizes of domains average to about 100 residues long

;Identification of domains depends on the explicit definition being used:
:* sequence domain: sequence inheritance
:* functional domain: modularized functional units
:* structural domain: based on atomic contacts (e.g. contact maps - hierarchial structural units of protein. may see subdomains)

===5.7.1 Domain databases===
;CATH:
Hierarchial classification of domains based off PDB. Mostly automated
:* Divide proteins into domains by: DETECTIVE, DOMAK, PUU
:* Manually curate and resolve conflicts arised from 3 streams of domain divisions (drawback: does not scale well this way..)
:* Classify domains into classes, homology, topology and architecture by: CATHEDRAL and SSAP

* '''DOMAK''': algorithm splits protein into units such that it max. intra-unit contacts and min. inter-unit-contacts
* '''DETECTIVE''': algorithm finds recognizable hydrophobic cores and with their shells to constitute domains
* '''PUU''': algorithm max. intra-unit contacts and min. inter-unit-contacts by building a "folding tree"

* '''CATHEDRAL''': fast prescreening domains against a database (based on secondary structure elements?)
* '''SSAP''': gives accurate structural alignment for domains

'''Domain swapping''' complicates issue..

Another related classification - protein families/superfamilies

However, boundaries between families are not always obvious, 
and within family might be non-homologous sequences due to convergent evolution.

;CDD (Conserved Domain Database):
Integrated domain database tool by NCBI. Combining structural domains from CATH and SCOP (discontinued), and sequence domains from Pfam.
:* Sequences are cross-referenced in many sequence databases.
:* ?Are structural domains cross-referenced as well?

PDB cross-references all of CATH, SCOP, Pfam.

;Activity 1 - Explore CATH database with Mbp1 protein
1. Go to http://www.cathdb.info/ and search "1BM8"

2. There are matching CATH superfamilies, domains, and PDB references.

3. The '''CATH ID''' (hierarchial) is 3.10.260.10

4. On the top, "Browse"

5. Under CATH classification, the protein (domain) is Alpha Beta-Roll

6. Under "3.10 Roll", there are lots of different topologies. Each one has a representative fold that can be clicked, and viewed to the left.

7. Each 3rd level group (topology group) pretty much consist of a non-homologous group. 3.10.260 points to Mlu1-box binding protein -- DNA binding domain

8 The 4th level groups the same topology group into different homology groups. e.g. 3.10.260.10 points to Transcription regulator HTH, APSES-type DNA-binding domain

9. On the left you can "Go to Superfamily". I guess at the homology level would be what we call "superfamily"? There are useful tools in the link.

;Activity 2 - Explore CDD with Mbp1_ERECY
1. Go to the [https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/protein/XP_003645298.1?report=genbank&log$=protalign&blast_rank=1&RID=UT6SVB5U014 NCBI entry for Mbp1_ERECY]

2. On the right, "CDD Search Results"

3. For each entry/accession of domain annotation, can link to the domain entry with description, statistics, and protein sequence alignments

4. "Search for similar domain architectures" redirects to CDART. Supposedly a very useful tool.

===5.7.2 Domain boundaries===
;Objective:
Explore the fluid definitions of domain boundaries.

;Activity - Explore domain boundaries of APSES and KilA-N in 1BM8 PDB structure.
1. <code>open 1bm8</code> and use "Interactive 1" preset to view as ribbons in rainbow colours.

2. Go to '''InterPro''' (EBI's tool) at http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/ and search "P39678" by text.

3. Under "Domain" and "Repeat", aligned to the N-terminus I can find IPR003163 (5-111), IPR018004 (22-88), PF04383 (23-88), and additionally SM01252 (22-105)
:* ?What is SMART domain?

4. The domains are not quite clickable, but they do seem to describe the same protein, albeit somewhat different boundaries.

5. If I were to use NCBI to identify conserved domains for S. cerevisiae Mbp1, I get a slightly different definition for the N-terminal domain annotation "KilA-N" as 19-93

'''Even though the annotation ID is also Pfam PF04383, it is different from what I get from EBI!'''

6. In Chimera, colour the whole chain white. Then, colour the protein in terms of different domain definitions

Resulting picture:

[[File:domain_boundaries.png|500px]]
* Yellow - IPR003163 (5-111)
* Orange - PF04383 (19-93)
* Red - PF04383 (23-88)

It becomes apparent that the latter two definitions are missing out a helix and a anti-parallel beta-hairpin.

If you ask me, I think this is a big deal because the helix looks like a part of a helix-turn-helix in the structure,

and the beta-hairpin stacks along another beta-sheet common in three definitions.

'''I would certainly expect inclusion of those segments affect the folding of this unit!'''

7. Hide all ribbons. Show Atoms/bonds for the protein. Change the radius of bonds to 0.4 under Inspect > Bonds menu bottom right.

8. "Tools" > "Surface/Binding Analysis" > "FindHbond" with Line width set to 5.0

Most of the hydrogen bonds are formed involving backbones. In particular, the aforementioned beta-sheet components has all three colours participating:

[[File:bb_hb.jpg|500px]]

Backbone to backbone hydrogen bonds reveal that a series of anti-parallel beta-sheets (left side of the structure image) that are incomplete in orange and red definitions.

[[File:sc_hb.jpg|500px]]

There are barely any sidechain-sidechain hydrogen bonds. Alpha carbons are artificially joined by long bond-like representations.

;Conclusion:
'''Do not blindly trust any domain boundary definition! They are rather arbitrary. Inspect structure if available.'''

==5.6 Molecular Forcefields==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 15 min; taken 10 min; date started: 2019-10-25; date completed: 2019-10-25

[[User:Zhi Wei Zeng|Zhi Wei Zeng]] ([[User talk:Zhi Wei Zeng|talk]]) 18:37, 26 October 2019 (EDT)
</div>

;To calculate the energy of a biomolecule at a specific conformation

;Molecular Mechanics Forcefields:
:* e.g. GROMOS, CHARMM, AMBER etc.
:* classical treatment of interactions specified by bonds, angles, dihedrals, vdW, Coulombic
:* Entropy not directly accounted for

;Empirical (Statistical) Forcefields:
:* Energy: related to inversed Boltzmann of frequencies of observed states

==5.5 PDB File Analysis==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 2 h; taken 110 min; date started: 2019-10-24; date completed: 2019-10-25

[[User:Zhi Wei Zeng|Zhi Wei Zeng]] ([[User talk:Zhi Wei Zeng|talk]]) 00:07, 25 October 2019 (EDT)
</div>

;Objective: Analyze .pdb files in R

;Useful functions:
:* abline(): add straight lines to a plot
:* densCols(<vector>): produce a vector of colours used for smooth density contour plots
:* smoothScatter(): scatter plots with smooth density contour plots
:* MASS::kde2d(): create a 2D [https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kernel_density_estimation kernel density estimation] (for contour plots)
:* contour()
:* filled.contour()
:* persp(): perspective plot (wired surface)
:* par()
:* layout(): set complex plot layout arrangements
:* bio3d::read.pdb(<path>): returns a named list of information retrieved from pdb file specified by <path>
:* bio3d::pdbseq(<pdb_object>): get a named vector of one-letter-code sequence from pdb. Names are the corresponding residue numbers
:* bio3d::torsion.pdb(<pdb_object>): returns a named list of all kinds of torsion angle information
:* bio3d::aa321() & bio3d::aa123(): interconversion between 3-letter and 1-letter codes of amino acids
:* bio3d::plot.bio3d(): modified plotting function with specific handy pdb functionalities (e.g. plot B-factor along sequence)
:* bio3d::dssp()
:* bio3d::dist.xyz(A,B): distance between coordinates represented in A and B. A and B are vectors with 3N elements. Each are grouped in consecutive 3 as coord. Returns matrix of pairwise distances.

===5.5.1 Working through RPR-SX-PDB.R===
;Install bio3d and hexbin
<source lang="R">
install.packages(c("bio3d", "hexbin"))
</source>

<div class="toccolours mw-collapsible mw-collapsed" style="width:90%; margin-left: 10px; padding-right: 15px">
'''''Installation messages'''''
<div class="mw-collapsible-content">
<code>
WARNING: Rtools is required to build R packages but is not currently installed. Please download and install the appropriate version of Rtools before proceeding:

https://cran.rstudio.com/bin/windows/Rtools/
Installing packages into ‘C:/Users/Wilson/Documents/R/win-library/3.6’
(as ‘lib’ is unspecified)
trying URL 'https://cran.rstudio.com/bin/windows/contrib/3.6/bio3d_2.3-4.zip'
Content type 'application/zip' length 3640992 bytes (3.5 MB)
downloaded 3.5 MB

trying URL 'https://cran.rstudio.com/bin/windows/contrib/3.6/hexbin_1.27.3.zip'
Content type 'application/zip' length 931691 bytes (909 KB)
downloaded 909 KB

package ‘bio3d’ successfully unpacked and MD5 sums checked
package ‘hexbin’ successfully unpacked and MD5 sums checked

The downloaded binary packages are in
	C:\Users\Wilson\AppData\Local\Temp\RtmpwP9hs6\downloaded_packages
</code>
</div>
</div>

;Activity 1 - Examine plain-text 1BM8.pdb
:* Resolution: 1.71 Å

:* The first residue in SEQRES is the same as in ATOM

:* There are 83 water molecules (weird that the residue number is not continuous?!)

:* N-terminal and C-terminal are missing some hydrogens

Line 131-136: implicit sequence == explicit sequence for 1BM8.pdb

;Activity 2 - Ramanchandran plot analysis

Line 210: These are the lines showing residues that are in the outlying left-handed helix region
     eleno elety resid chain resno      phi      psi
 84     84    CA   SER     A    11 52.88084 36.95115
 293   293    CA   ASP     A    32 65.77463 14.94939
 406   406    CA   ASN     A    44 69.84793 27.66016
 887   887    CA   SER     A    91 44.70111 54.55245

Check these residues in Chimera: Command: <code>display :11,32,44,91</code>

Turns out these residues are in the loop/turn regions.

;Activity 3 - Density plots
Line 247:
<code>iNA <- c(which(is.na(tor$phi)), which(is.na(tor$psi)))</code>

iNA has indices for which phi or psi is not defined, such as the first and the last protein residues and water.

;Activity 4 - Check for cis-peptide bonds
Line 407-409:
The peptide bond is expected to be planar (0 or 180 degrees in dihedral angle). Dihedral angles are defined from -180 to 180 degrees. So those seemingly "jumping" values are actually quite close.

It can be fixed (Line 410-411).

;Activity 5 - Explore analysis of hydrogen bonds
Line 772:
Without importing bio3d with library(), this line should be <code>pdb <- bio3d::read.pdb(myPDBs[i])</code>

Line 792: why is it equal sign??

Line 817-819: Why do you think these distributions are different?

Distribution of HB distance for alpha helices is more spread out and average at a longer distance.

Distribution of HB distance for beta sheets is more concentrated around a smaller distance with tailing towards a larger distance.

: Perhaps the preferred geometry/angle of the hydrogen bonds are different for sheets versus for helices?

At what distance do you think H-bonds have the lowest energy?

: The distance with the highest frequency. For alpha-helices it would be 3.4 Å, while for beta-sheets it would be 2.8 Å.

==5.4 Small Molecules==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 2 h; taken 80 min; date started: 2019-10-24; date completed: 2019-10-24

[[User:Zhi Wei Zeng|Zhi Wei Zeng]] ([[User talk:Zhi Wei Zeng|talk]]) 18:23, 24 October 2019 (EDT)
</div>

;PDB has its own chemical database: Chemical Component Dictionary

;Access:
:* PDBeChem (EBI)
:* Ligand Expo (PDB)

;SMILE (Simplified molecular-input line-entry system) string: PDB "search by ligand" converts the chemical structure to a '''SMILE string''' that can be used to generate coordinates in Chimera.

===5.4.1 Explore caffeine through various databases===
;Activity 1 - Explore on DrugBank
: Downloadable items include PDB, SMILES, MOL, SDF, 3D-SDF, InChI

;Activity 2 - Explore on PubChem (NCBI) and search by drawing a structure
1. '''Structure search has moved. Click "Draw Structure"'''

2. Search for this structure:

[[File:caffeine_chemstruc.png|200px]]

3. The only result is "Caffeine". PubChemCID = 2519

 The SMILE string is CN1C=NC2=C1C(=O)N(C(=O)N2C)C

===5.4.2 Build the structure from SMILE===
;Activity 3 - Build structure in Chimera
1. Tools > Structure Editing > Build Structure

2. Use the SMILE string to build

3. Actions > Color > by element

[[File:caffeine_chimera.png|200px]]

4. Actions > Surface > show

5. Select the surface, then selection inspector, inspect MSMS surface and change vertex density to 50.0

6. Actions > Color > all options > cornflower blue (apply to surfaces only)

7. Actions > Surface > Transparency > 50%

8. Result in wall-eyed stereo view:

[[File:caffeine_stereo.png|400px]]

9. (3D stereo view practice)

===5.4.3 Superposition of small molecule into complex===
1. Chimera "open 3g6m"

2. Hide protein ribbons and atoms/bonds (there are 2 caffeine molecules in the complex!)

3. Hide one caffeine molecule from the complex <code>~display #1:1</code>

4. Inspect atom notations, here's the command in Chimera I use: <code>match #0@N3,C6,N4,C3,C4,C5,N1,C2,N2,C8,O2,C7,O1,C1 #1:427@N1,C2,N3,C4,C5,C6,N7,C8,N9,C10,O11,C12,O13,C14</code>

Before Matching...

[[File:before_matching.png|500px]]

After Matching...

[[File:after_matching.png|300px]]

==5.3 Molecular Graphics: UCSF Chimera==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 4 h; taken 3.5+ h; date started: 2019-10-22; date completed: 2019-10-23

[[User:Zhi Wei Zeng|Zhi Wei Zeng]] ([[User talk:Zhi Wei Zeng|talk]]) 18:23, 24 October 2019 (EDT)
</div>

;Activity 1 - Going through getting started tutorial
:* a useful Menu functionality: Select > Selection Mode

'''''Useful Commands'''''
* open <pdb_code>
* close <modelID>
* display <atom_spec>: display atoms specified. Doc for atom specification for Chimera is [https://www.rbvi.ucsf.edu/chimera/docs/UsersGuide/midas/frameatom_spec.html here]
* ribbon: show ribbon (<code>~ribbon</code> would be hide ribbon)
* start <tool>: invoke Chimera tool <tool>
* color/col <color_name> <spec>: (special commands: "col byelement", "col by het")
* represent/rep <style> <spec>
* rlabel <selection>: show residue label for <selection>
* label <selection>: show atom label for <selection>
* select <atom_spec>: make a selection (<code>select up</code> would upgrade selection to the whole residue, similar to "same residue as ..." in VMD)
* show <selection>
* surface/surf

* <code>~</code> opposite operator
* <code>:</code> residue name/number specification
* <code>#</code> model specification
* <code>.</code> chain ID specification
* <code>@</code> atom name specification
* <code>=</code> partial wildcard (comparable to * in Shell)
* <code>?</code> single character wildcard (comparable to . in Shell)
* <code>,</code> "OR" operator
* sel: current selection

;Activity 2 - Practising stereo viewing (divergent)

1. open 1bm8

2. preset apply pub 1

3. Turn on depth cueing

4. Tools > Depiction > Rainbow

5. Tools > Viewing Controls > Camera, select "camera mode" as "wall-eye stereo"

6. <span style="color:red">The separation between my pupils is 7 cm.</span> So I will make the separation between the two images about 6 cm.

7. View it as in the instruction in the course material [http://steipe.biochemistry.utoronto.ca/abc/index.php/BIN-SX-Chimera].

8. It worked like wonders! The 3D view was especially obvious when I rotate the structure with mouse, and when my eyes got tired.

3D image sustained for quite a separation of my eyes from the screen (until I mis-clicked elsewhere and it's all disrupted..)

[[File:1BM8_stereo.png|500px]]

;Activity 3 - Ramanchandran plot

(Straightforward. In the Model Panel directly)

;Activity 4 - B-factor colouring

Hydrogens by default is coloured with the lowest B-factor (blue)?!

[[File:bfactor_render.png|400px]]

;Activity 5 - Viewing coulombic surface

(Viewing Panel will be my best friend)

(DNA-binding site is probably the one underneath, very blue and positive and looks like there's a pocket)

[[File:coulombic_mbp1.png|400px]]

;Activity 6 - Is the sequence in Chimera implicit or explicit?

1. open 1bm8

2. File > Save PDB, call it "1bm8_Q1A.pdb"

3. Delete the following lines:
 ATOM      6  CG  GLN A   4      -0.797   3.008  17.820  1.00 57.21           C
 ATOM      7  CD  GLN A   4      -0.029   2.066  18.730  1.00 60.18           C
 ATOM      8  OE1 GLN A   4       1.135   2.325  19.071  1.00 61.12           O
 ATOM      9  NE2 GLN A   4      -0.673   0.970  19.131  1.00 61.27           N
 ATOM     13 HE21 GLN A   4      -0.200   0.339  19.714  1.00  0.00           H
 ATOM     14 HE22 GLN A   4      -1.594   0.835  18.832  1.00  0.00           H

(I think the following lines are not from the sidechain, so I retained them)
 ATOM     10  H1  GLN A   4      -1.493   5.767  14.644  1.00  0.00           H
 ATOM     11  H2  GLN A   4      -0.148   4.764  14.393  1.00  0.00           H
 ATOM     12  H3  GLN A   4      -1.618   4.097  14.918  1.00  0.00           H

4. Rename the first residue GLN to ALA

5. Save and load in Chimera. Check with Favorites > Sequence

6. The first residue is denoted as "A". '''Therefore the residue identities in the Sequence tool is IMPLICIT!'''

[[File:proofimplicit.png|500px]]

==5.2 Protein Data Bank==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 1 h; taken 90 min; date started: 2019-10-21; date completed: 2019-10-21

[[User:Zhi Wei Zeng|Zhi Wei Zeng]] ([[User talk:Zhi Wei Zeng|talk]]) 18:23, 24 October 2019 (EDT)
</div>

===5.2.1 PDB files===
*flat file (no inherent indexing structure), column-formatted

;HEADER, COMPND, SOURCE: identity of the structure

;SEQRES: explicit sequence, the PDB-sequence for database searches, in the material the experimentalist actually worked with
:* not to be confused with implicit sequence, which is the sequence as registered with coordinates (can have unmodelled parts missing)

;Insertion codes: 
:* Sometimes a sequence number will be followed by a capital letter (e.g. 23 followed by 23A). This is used in sequences that are longer than other homologous counterparts.
:* Used to maintain common numbering scheme within a homologous family

;ATOM: protein or nucleic acids

;HETATM: ligands, cofactors, solvents

;Occupancy: fraction of sites that are occupied by that atom (often seen as 1.0, but modelled coordinates without experimental support have occupancy of 0.0)

;B-factor: thermal fluctuation of atoms related to mean coord displacement if fluctuations are isotropic
:* <math>B = 8\pi^2 <\mathbf{x}^2></math>
:* Often hard to interpret because of anisotropic fluctuation of atoms, poor crystals etc. But generally confidence of position?

;For biological inferences, make sure to distinguish whether we are looking at asymmetric unit or biological unit! It's also not always obvious whether symmetry is induced by crystallization.

===5.2.2 Alternative structural services===
;[https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/MMDB/mmdb.shtml MMDB]: a structural database by NCBI

;[http://ndbserver.rutgers.edu/ Nucleic Acid Structural Database (NDB)]

;[http://www.ebi.ac.uk/thornton-srv/databases/cgi-bin/pdbsum/GetPage.pl?pdbcode=index.html PDBsum]: secondary database by EBI. Has analysis and interpretation information

===5.2.3 Navigation of RCSB PDB website===
;Objective: get more familiar with RCSB PDB

1. Search Mbp1

2. Found 3 entries for the ''S. cerevisiae'' Mbp1 protein (keyword search IS indeed bad..):
:* PDB codes: 1BM8, 1MB1, 1L3G

3. Navigate the entry 1BM8:
:* Can download PDB-file or biological assembly?!
:* Protein feature view shows domain topology
:* In this example, asymmetric unit is the biological assembly

4. Go to "3D View": as expected, the core of the protein is mainly hydrophobic

5. Go to "Annotations": Search parameters = CathTree Search for Mlu1-box Binding Protein; DNA-binding Domain (3.10.260)
:* There are currently 6 entries in PDB with this domain/fold (including 1BM8)

6. Go to "Sequence": can annotate sequence with DSSP secondary structure propensities and annotate domains

7. Go to "Sequence Similarity": self-explanatory, basically BLAST-like?

8. Go to "Structural Similarity":
:* determined by jFATCAT-rigid algorithm? [http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/explore/structureCluster.do?structureId=1BM8]
:* Has P-value, RMSD, Score, percent identiy, Cov? (probably described in the publication above)
:* Clicking entries under "Domain 2" will go to the same type of page but for this new domain
:* Clicking "view" under "Results" gives a lot more functionalities worth exploring. Related to structural alignments.

9. Go to "Experiment": can find experimental details of structural determination for this entry.

==5.1 Structural Concepts==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 1 h; taken 30 min; date started: 2019-10-15; date completed: 2019-10-15

[[User:Zhi Wei Zeng|Zhi Wei Zeng]] ([[User talk:Zhi Wei Zeng|talk]]) 13:10, 15 October 2019 (EDT)
</div>

===5.1.1 Abstraction and storage===
;Structures are time-averaged and population-averaged.

;Computable abstraction of structure:
:* coordinates
:* chemical types (e.g. atom types)

;Quality metrics:
:* resolution
:* R-work, R-free
:* bond length and angle deviations
:* coordinate error (e.g. from diffraction data)

;Choosing the right structural model for analyses:
:* Quality of the dataset (raw data) and model-building (overfitting based on R-ratios)
:* Method of structure determination
:* Experimental conditions (native environment?)
:* Model completeness (fewer missing segments)
:* When making inferences about related proteins, the sequence similarity is important
:* Space group and crystal contacts
:* When analysis pertains to ligand binding, the holo structures would be desirable

===5.1.2 Visualization and interpretation===
;Types of tructure representation depends on purpose.

;Stereo view! Trick my eyes into seeing 3D with left and right images?

;Interpretation: structure as collection of features

{{Vspace}}
