=5 Structural Bioinformatics=
==5.2 Protein Data Bank==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 1 h; taken 90 min; date started: 2019-10-21; date completed: 2019-10-21

~~~~
</div>

===5.2.1 PDB files===
*flat file (no inherent indexing structure), column-formatted

;HEADER, COMPND, SOURCE: identity of the structure

;SEQRES: explicit sequence, the PDB-sequence for database searches, in the material the experimentalist actually worked with
:* not to be confused with implicit sequence, which is the sequence as registered with coordinates (can have unmodelled parts missing)

;Insertion codes: 
:* Sometimes a sequence number will be followed by a capital letter (e.g. 23 followed by 23A). This is used in sequences that are longer than other homologous counterparts.
:* Used to maintain common numbering scheme within a homologous family

;ATOM: protein or nucleic acids

;HETATM: ligands, cofactors, solvents

;Occupancy: fraction of sites that are occupied by that atom (often seen as 1.0, but modelled coordinates without experimental support have occupancy of 0.0)

;B-factor: thermal fluctuation of atoms related to mean coord displacement if fluctuations are isotropic
:* <math>B = 8\pi^2 <\mathbf{x}^2></math>
:* Often hard to interpret because of anisotropic fluctuation of atoms, poor crystals etc. But generally confidence of position?

;For biological inferences, make sure to distinguish whether we are looking at asymmetric unit or biological unit! It's also not always obvious whether symmetry is induced by crystallization.

===5.2.2 Alternative structural services===
;[https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/MMDB/mmdb.shtml MMDB]: a structural database by NCBI

;[http://ndbserver.rutgers.edu/ Nucleic Acid Structural Database (NDB)]

;[http://www.ebi.ac.uk/thornton-srv/databases/cgi-bin/pdbsum/GetPage.pl?pdbcode=index.html PDBsum]: secondary database by EBI. Has analysis and interpretation information

===5.2.3 Navigation of RCSB PDB website===
;Objective: get more familiar with RCSB PDB

1. Search Mbp1

2. Found 3 entries for the ''S. cerevisiae'' Mbp1 protein (keyword search IS indeed bad..):
:* PDB codes: 1BM8, 1MB1, 1L3G

3. Navigate the entry 1BM8:
:* Can download PDB-file or biological assembly?!
:* Protein feature view shows domain topology
:* In this example, asymmetric unit is the biological assembly

4. Go to "3D View": as expected, the core of the protein is mainly hydrophobic

5. Go to "Annotations": Search parameters = CathTree Search for Mlu1-box Binding Protein; DNA-binding Domain (3.10.260)
:* There are currently 6 entries in PDB with this domain/fold (including 1BM8)

6. Go to "Sequence": can annotate sequence with DSSP secondary structure propensities and annotate domains

7. Go to "Sequence Similarity": self-explanatory, basically BLAST-like?

8. Go to "Structural Similarity":
:* determined by jFATCAT-rigid algorithm? [http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/explore/structureCluster.do?structureId=1BM8]
:* Has P-value, RMSD, Score, percent identiy, Cov? (probably described in the publication above)
:* Clicking entries under "Domain 2" will go to the same type of page but for this new domain
:* Clicking "view" under "Results" gives a lot more functionalities worth exploring. Related to structural alignments.

9. Go to "Experiment": can find experimental details of structural determination for this entry.

==5.1 Structural Concepts==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 1 h; taken 30 min; date started: 2019-10-15; date completed: 2019-10-15

[[User:Zhi Wei Zeng|Zhi Wei Zeng]] ([[User talk:Zhi Wei Zeng|talk]]) 13:10, 15 October 2019 (EDT)
</div>

===5.1.1 Abstraction and storage===
;Structures are time-averaged and population-averaged.

;Computable abstraction of structure:
:* coordinates
:* chemical types (e.g. atom types)

;Quality metrics:
:* resolution
:* R-work, R-free
:* bond length and angle deviations
:* coordinate error (e.g. from diffraction data)

;Choosing the right structural model for analyses:
:* Quality of the dataset (raw data) and model-building (overfitting based on R-ratios)
:* Method of structure determination
:* Experimental conditions (native environment?)
:* Model completeness (fewer missing segments)
:* When making inferences about related proteins, the sequence similarity is important
:* Space group and crystal contacts
:* When analysis pertains to ligand binding, the holo structures would be desirable

===5.1.2 Visualization and interpretation===
;Types of tructure representation depends on purpose.

;Stereo view! Trick my eyes into seeing 3D with left and right images?

;Interpretation: structure as collection of features

{{Vspace}}
