=8 Gene Expression and Functional Bioinformatics=
==8.5 Gene Ontology (GO)==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 1.5 h; taken 75 min; date started: 2019-11-30; date completed: 2019-11-30

~~~~
</div>

;Motivation:
:* Function is an elusive term. Typically not observable on its own
:* Ontology: language "engineering" to make function tractable
:* No automatic way to structure and categorize system relationships into insights of what the purpose of a biomolecular system is

;Gene Ontology:
:* Consortium that maintains controlled vocabulary of terms, establish relationships between attributes, annotate genes
:* '''Root nodes: Cellular Component, Molecular Function, Biological Process'''

;Gene Ontology Annotation Evidence Codes:
:* http://wiki.geneontology.org/index.php/Guide_to_GO_Evidence_Codes

;Major Challenge:
Quantifying similarity between two genes for function comparison, categorization of genes, annotation of gene sets, and prediction of gene function

;Managing GO data:
:* Download ontology downloadables are desirable. Files are well structured and parsable
:* In R, Bioconductor has many packages that can be used for analysis

;GO slims:
Or "GO subsets". "High level summaries of an area of biology based on selected GO terms" [https://www.ebi.ac.uk/QuickGO/help/slims]

===8.5.1 AmiGO===
AmiGo: A convenient online GO browser?

;Activity - Navigate GO with Mbp1

1. Go to http://geneontology.org/ and search "Mbp1"

2. Obtained a AmiGO 2 interface. Select "Genes and gene products".

3. A list of 8 hits were obtained. Each hit has info about organism, type of gene product, source of information, and synonyms

4. Select "MBP1" with organism "Saccharomyces cerevisiae S288C", synonymous to "YDL056W" (SGD ID)


"MBP1" has a green box around it. I am not sure what it means?

The first section "Gene Product Information" is a short summary of basic info and cross-references of the gene MBP1

The second section "Gene Product Association" gives browsable table of annotations. For each annotation:
* Contributor database
* GO class (I guess each class has an associated GO ID?)
* GO Evidence Code
* Reference: It may either be a PMID, which links to a publication, or a GO_REF type ID, presumably specifying annotation automatically or manually, or through other means of association
* Evidence with: If GO_REF type ID is given in "Reference", this would refer to an entity in Contributor database from which such annotation is transferred from?
* Date
* PANTHER family (don't know what this is)


5. On the left, can apply filters for results. Under "Ontology (aspect)", "C" for Cellular Component, "F" for Molecular Function, "P" for Biological Process.

6. Go to the link to GO class "positive regulation of transcription involved in G1/S transition of mitotic cell cycle". This is a "P" ontology.

7. Filter by "Organism" with "Saccharomyces cerevisiae S288C".

A quick overview of genes show that "SWI6" comes up frequently. Among others are "MBP1", "RME1", "SPT6"

8. Under "Graph Views" tab, go to "QuickGO" link for this term.


In particular on the page, there is an "Ancestor Chart" which is essentially a directed acyclic graph showing relationships of GO-terms with the current one included.

Legend is available showing what relationship each colour of a directed edge represents. Can be useful to explore a more complete picture of function this gene involved in.

Other viewing options available under this tab too. More specific subsets of this entry in the "big graph" can be found under "Inferred Tree View" or "Neighborhood" tabs.


9. Under "Inferred Tree View", find the GO term which the current term "GO:0071931" is part of. This directs to the entry "GO:0000082 G1/S transition of mitotic cell cycle".

10. Under the "Annotation" tab, there are currently 3243 records. Under filter "GO class (direct)", it becomes apparent that it also includes entries annotated to its descendent terms (including "GO:0071931")


==8.4 GEO2R==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 2 h; taken 5 h; date started: 2019-11-30; date completed: 2019-11-30

[[User:Zhi Wei Zeng|Zhi Wei Zeng]] ([[User talk:Zhi Wei Zeng|talk]]) 17:52, 30 November 2019 (EST)
</div>

;Useful functions:
:* GEOquery::getGEO(<accession_string>)
:* Biobase::exprs(<dataset>): display expression data table

;Activity - Experience with GEO2R by going through "RPR-GEO2R.R"

Line 100-112:
Subsetting retrieved GEO record should be performed. In case there are multiple experiments done with different platforms. The GEO record retrieved is a list of ExpressionSet class.

But even if that is not the case, the record list object still has a length of 1.

Line 134-138:
 assayData: 6228 features, 13 samples

I guess "features" here correspond to genes? 13 samples must be samples taken from time intervals in this case.

Line 147-155:
Each cell contains log ratio of expression of a given gene (row) at a given timepoint/sample (column)

At intervals, experiment measures the expression levels of genes at regular cell cycle time points

Line 174-178:
These are log ratio of expression of genes.

Seems like on average expression levels of all genes considered herein are more or less constant over the cell cycle.

Line 200-202:
The genes overexpressing and underexpressing becomes apparent at time points 30 min and 60 min, as the distributions at these timepoints are wider.

I find it strange that at 90 min and 120 min, the expression levels normalize back to around timepoint 0 min. But 90 min is the midpoint of the second cell cycle?

Also find it strange that at 60 min, approximately the end of the fist cell cycle, there are more differentially expressed genes just like at midpoint of 30 min..

Line 219-220:
Re-order the samples so that samples taken at the same time within a cell cycle are close together for clustering.

Line 221:
<code>as.factor()</code> turn them into categorical variables before analysis. Hugely useful.

Line 246-251:
Row-wise analysis for individual genes. Though not all rows are genes. There are blanks and non-yeast controls, presumably required for this type of experiment.

But mostly, they are yeast genes in SGD format.

<span style="color:red">"SGD_features.tab" looks like a nightmare. Who thought this is a good idea?</span>

<source lang="R">
# This line takes a very long time to done correctly
# At first I assumed "SGD_features.tab" is formatted poorly, so I use fill = TRUE
# I could not get the nrow(SGD_features) correctly, but opening as csv works properly.
# I pinned down the first instance of problematic line to be Line 75 in "SGD_features.tab"
# There is a single quote ' in the description of Line 75, where "3'" is mentioned
# "SGD_features.README.txt" had some quote issues as well. In ?read.table, looks like the argument quote solves the problem
# fill = TRUE is not necessary. Turns out the format is done nicely (I guess...) for parsing 
SGD_features <- read.table("./data/SGD_features.tab", sep = "\t", quote = "", stringsAsFactors=FALSE)

# Name its columns according to "SGD_features.README.txt"
colnames(SGD_features) <- c("Primary SGDID", 
                            "Feature type", 
                            "Feature qualifier", 
                            "Feature name", 
                            "Standard gene name", 
                            "Alias", 
                            "Parent feature name",
                            "Secondary SGDID",
                            "Chromosome",
                            "Start_coordinate",
                            "Stop_coordinate",
                            "Strand",
                            "Genetic position",
                            "Coordinate version",
                            "Sequence version",
                            "Description")

#Select essential information and rename to be consistent with provided source code
subset <- c(1:5, 16)
SGD_features <- SGD_features[,subset]
colnames(SGD_features) <- c("SGDID",
                            "type",
                            "qual",
                            "sysName",
                            "name",
                            "description")

# Remove all rows that do not have a systematic name
hasSysName <- as.logical(nchar(SGD_features[, "sysName"]))
SGD_features <- SGD_features[hasSysName,]

# All systematic names are unique?
(! any(duplicated(SGD_features[,"sysName"])))

# Name rows after systematic names
rownames(SGD_features) <- SGD_features[,"sysName"]

# How many "genes" in the expression dataset is not in SGD features (yeast genome)?
notInFeatures <- setdiff(rownames(Biobase::exprs(GSE3635)), rownames(SGD_features))
(length(notInFeatures))
# Above is not actually the number of genes not in yeast genome. Some of them were actually names of controls
# The number of yeast reading frame that is not in SGD features database is:
(length(notInFeatures[-1:-11])) #63

# How many / which genes in the feature table do not have expression data?
noData <- setdiff(rownames(SGD_features), rownames(Biobase::exprs(GSE3635))) 
#1907 entries. Though not all of them are genes though e.g. centromere. 
# grep() according to SGD_features[,"type"] can be helpful for that purpose
</source>

Line 330:
Should be <code>(iExprs <- which(Biobase::featureNames(GSE3635) == SGD_features$sysName[iFeature]))</code>

Plotting of some selected genes:
<source lang="R">
plotGene <- function(gName, color) {
    #Make sure it is uppercase
    gName <- toupper(gName)
    # Get index in SGD_features where the input gene occurs
    iFeature <- which(SGD_features$name == gName)
    # Get index in expression data GSE3635 where the input gene occurs
    iExprs <- which(Biobase::featureNames(GSE3635) == SGD_features$sysName[iFeature])

    # Plot it
    plot(seq(0, 120, by = 10),
         Biobase::exprs(GSE3635)[iExprs, ],
         main = "Expression profile",
         xlab = "time (min)",
         ylab = "expression",
         ylim = range(c(-2,2)),
         type = "b",
         col = color)

    # Description
    cat(sprintf("Gene Description: %s", SGD_features$description[iFeature]))
}

getColors <- function(numColors) {
    # Divide into intervals, whose values will be assigned to colors
    unitVals <- 1 / numColors
    comp1 <- seq(1, 0, length.out=numColors)
    comp2 <- seq(0, 1, length.out=numColors)

    colorOut <- c()
    for (i in 1:numColors) {
        colorOut[i] <- rgb(comp1[i], comp2[i], 0) # This is just the red mode. I am not familiar with how to select blue modes elegently in R
    }
    return(colorOut)
}

plotGeneSeries <- function(gNames) {
    allColors <- getColors(length(gNames))
    for (i in seq_along(gNames)) {
        color <- allColors[i]
        plotGene(gNames[i], color)
        # https://stackoverflow.com/questions/2564258/plot-two-graphs-in-same-plot-in-r
        par(new=TRUE)
    }
    legend("topleft", gNames, fill = allColors, bty = "n")
    abline(h =  0, col = "#00000055")
    abline(v = 60, col = "#00000055") 
}

onGenes <- c('Cdc14', 'Mbp1', 'Swi6', 'Swi4', 'Whi5', 'Cdc28', 'Cln1', 'Cln2', 'Cln3')
plotGeneSeries(onGenes)

offGenes <- c('Rad53', 'Cdc28', 'Clb1', 'Clb2', 'Clb6', 'Nrm1')
plotGeneSeries(offGenes)

hkGenes <- c('Act1', 'Alg9')
plotGeneSeries(hkGenes)
</source>

[[File:OnGEO.png|500px]]

[[File:OffGEO.png|500px]]

[[File:hkGEO.png|500px]]

Line 419-422:
Design matrix needed to treat factors for statistical tests

Print the top 10 genes differentially expressed as identified by limma R-package:
<source lang="R">
#    Print the descriptions of the top ten differentially expressed genes
#    and comment on what they have in common (or not).

#Top 10 differentially expressed identified by R-package limma tools
topTenSysName <- myTable[1:10 , "ID"]
SGD_descriptions <- SGD_features$description
names(SGD_descriptions) <- SGD_features$sysName

#Retrieve descriptions by names
topDescriptions <- SGD_descriptions[topTenSysName]

for (i in seq_along(topDescriptions)) {
    print(topDescriptions[i])
}
</source>

I see one gene that does not exist in SGD, namely "YML117W-A".

I see some genes involved in chromosome modification and processing, DNA replication, and cell cycle progressing which seem to make sense.

There are also two enzymes that do not seem very relevant based on the descriptions..

 YMR215W: "Putative 1,3-beta-glucanosyltransferase; has similarity go other GAS family members; low abundance, possibly inactive member of the GAS family of GPI-containing proteins; localizes to the cell wall; mRNA induced during sporulation" 
 YEL032W: "Protein involved in DNA replication; component of the Mcm2-7 hexameric helicase complex that binds chromatin as a part of the pre-replicative complex" 
 YBL003C: "Histone H2A; core histone protein required for chromatin assembly and chromosome function; one of two nearly identical (see also HTA1) subtypes; DNA damage-dependent phosphorylation by Mec1p facilitates DNA repair; acetylated by Nat4p" 
 YIL123W: "Protein of the SUN family (Sim1p, Uth1p, Nca3p, Sun4p); may participate in DNA replication; promoter contains SCB regulation box at -300 bp indicating that expression may be cell cycle-regulated; SIM1 has a paralog, SUN4, that arose from the whole genome duplication" 
 YGR098C: "Separase, a caspase-like cysteine protease; promotes sister chromatid separation by mediating dissociation of the cohesin Scc1p from chromatin; inhibits protein phosphatase 2A-Cdc55p to promote mitotic exit; inhibited by Pds1p; relative distribution to the nucleus increases upon DNA replication stress" 
 YML117W-A: (does not exist in SGD)
 YNL031C: "Histone H3; core histone protein required for chromatin assembly, part of heterochromatin-mediated telomeric and HM silencing; one of two identical histone H3 proteins (see HHT1); regulated by acetylation, methylation, and phosphorylation; H3K14 acetylation plays an important role in the unfolding of strongly positioned nucleosomes during repair of UV damage" 
 YJL137C: "Glycogenin glucosyltransferase; self-glucosylating initiator of glycogen synthesis, also glucosylates n-dodecyl-beta-D-maltoside; similar to mammalian glycogenin; GLG2 has a paralog, GLG1, that arose from the whole genome duplication" 
 YOR066W: "Activator of G1-specific transcription factors MBF and SBF; involved in regulation of the timing of G1-specific gene transcription and cell cycle initiation; localization is cell-cycle dependent and regulated by Cdc28p phosphorylation; MSA1 has a paralog, MSA2, that arose from the whole genome duplication" 
 YDR224C: "Histone H2B; core histone protein required for chromatin assembly and chromosome function; nearly identical to HTB2; Rad6p-Bre1p-Lge1p mediated ubiquitination regulates reassembly after DNA replication, transcriptional activation, meiotic DSB formation and H3 methylation" 

'''An approach to weigh in biology in addition to purely statistical measure - find correlation with genes ''known'' to be diff. expr. in cell cycle progression.

(Also, anti-correlated ones)

==8.3 Differential Expression Analysis==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 1.5 h; taken 1.5 h; date started: 2019-11-11; date completed: 2019-11-11

[[User:Zhi Wei Zeng|Zhi Wei Zeng]] ([[User talk:Zhi Wei Zeng|talk]]) 23:59, 11 November 2019 (EST)
</div>

Data come from high throughput methods.

;M/A plot:
M on the vertical axis and A on the horizontal axis. M is the log ratio of expression, and A is the average expression.
:* Consideration of whether a gene is '''significantly''' differentially expressed is probably affected by both (e.g. low A tends to be noisy).

GEO provides many tools for differential expression analysis

;Objective: Search for relevant information from GEO and identify significantly differentially expressed genes.

;Activity - Explore differential expression of Mbp1 and its target genes.

1. Go to NCBI GEO DataSets query page https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/gds/

2. Search the query ""cell cycle"[ti] AND "saccharomyces cerevisiae"[organism]". Filter the "Entry Type" to "DataSets"

3. There are 5 dataset entries. To follow the [http://steipe.biochemistry.utoronto.ca/abc/index.php/BIN-EXPR-DE#GEO2R instructions of the course], 
I will get the entry with Accession ID of GDS2347

4. The entry redirects to the DataSet Browser page https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sites/GDSbrowser?acc=GDS2347

5. See a table. There is a link to the "Reference Series", whose Accession ID is GSE3635. Go to this cross-referenced GEO Series https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE3635.

6. There are descriptions of experimental design and sample information, with the relevant citation.

Samples are taken at time points throughout the cell cycle. Cells were (obviously) synchronized a priori.

7. Do "Analyze with GEO2R" (https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/geo2r/?acc=GSE3635)

8. Define groups and assign samples to groups. Since the samples span two cell cycles (2x 60 min) at 10 min intervals. I will make 5 groups, each consisting of the same amount of time into the beginning of cell cycle.

 T0: 0 min & 60 min, N=2
 T1: 10 min & 70 min, N=2
 T2: 20 min & 80 min, N=2
 T3: 30 min & 90 min, N=2
 T4: 40 min & 100 min, N=2
 T5: 50 min & 110 min, N=2
 (Leave out 130 min sample)

9. From the tab "Value Distribution", the expression distribution of samples are more or less unbiased:

[[File:expr_boxplt.jpg|300px]]

10. Under "GEO2R", look at "Top 250".

 Many of the top hits are histone proteins and DNA replication machineries. They are expected to be differentially expressed throughout cell cycle.

 MBP1 is not one of the top 250 hits! Swi6 is but not one of the top hits among top 250.

<span style="color:red">The website is incredibly bad imo... Takes way too long than reasonable to display drop-down for each entry expression profile.</span>

 The algorithm finds genes that have high inter-group variances and low intra-group variances. It does not assume group-dependent patterns of expression.

11. Re-group the samples:

 A: 0 min, 10 min, 60 min, 70 min, N=4 (in between cell cycles)
 B: 30 min, 40 min, 90 min, 100 min, N=4 (in the middle of cell cycles)

Results are expected to change.

 Out of DSE1, DSE2, ERF3, HTA2, HTB2, and GAS3, only HTA2, HTB2, and GAS3 are in the top 250. MBP1 appears in top 250 while SWI6 is gone.

12. Search the query "(Mbp1 OR Swi6 OR Swi4 OR Nrm1 OR Cln1 OR Clb6 OR Act1 OR Alg9) AND GSE3635" in GEO Profiles.

13. Go to [https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/tools/profileGraph.cgi?ID=GDS2347:YDL056W entry of MBP1]. The graphical view of expression over time is more apparently cyclic. Can probably fit with a sine curve or calculate time-correlation.

14. R-scripts used for analysis is available for GEO2R


==8.2 The Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO) database==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 1.5 h; taken 1.5 h; date started: 2019-11-11; date completed: 2019-11-11

[[User:Zhi Wei Zeng|Zhi Wei Zeng]] ([[User talk:Zhi Wei Zeng|talk]]) 17:43, 11 November 2019 (EST)
</div>

Overview of GEO database: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4944384/

A very helpful overview of record types and data organization: https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/info/overview.html

;Retrieving GEO record:
GEO Accession Number
:* Types: Series (GSExxx), Sample (GSMxxx), Platform (GPLxxx) and DataSet (GDSxxx)

<span style="color:red">Key things to know for this session are these entry types</span>

Keyword search among databases
:* GEO DataSets: search for studies of interest. Entries/records commonly have Organism, Experiment Type & Design.
:* GEO Profiles: search for expression profile of genes

;Activity 1 - Give GEO Profiles a Try with MBP1
1. Search NCBI - GEO Profiles with the query "Mbp1 AND (Saccharomyces cerevisiae[Organism])"

2. Entries are annotated with GPLxxx platforms, GDSxxx datasets, dataset type, SGD ID for the protein YDL056W, and name "MBP1".
There is also a thumbnail clickable showing expression levels in all samples with graphics. Curated?

;GEO-BLAST:
Database contains all sequences from Microarrays participating in GEO DataSet from GenBank?

;GEO DataSet:
:* Can find info of other genes in this DataSet
:* Can compare 2 sets of samples with statistical tests
:* Can cluster heatmaps
:* Protocol and distribution of values of samples are viewable

;GEO Profile:
I use https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geoprofiles/16205984 as an example of GEO profile to inspect.
:* Can find profile neighbours, aka get profiles of genes of similar expression pattern '''within the same DataSet''' (based on Pearson corr. coeff. but it would be nice if the coeff. are displayed..)
:* Can find up-to-20 chromosome neighbours in the same DataSet
:* Other neighbours: Sequence neighbours (based on BLAST seq. similarity), homologene neighbours (from the same HomoloGene group)
:* Find pathway/cluster though "Pathways + GO"? <span style="color:red">I didn't see a "Find Pathways" button.. </span>

;GEO2R:
Analysis and visualization tools. Can be found in accession display for a GEO entry. Based on R-language.

;Genome Data Viewer:
Visualization.. Zoom in and zoom out?

;Downloads:
Often from GEO Series. Downloadable formats:
:* SOFT (Simple Omnibus Format in Text): plain-text
:* MINiML (MIAME Notation in Markup Language): XML
:* Series Matrix File(s): ?


==8.1 Analysis of Gene Expression==

<div class="time-estimate">
Time estimated: 0.5 h; taken 20 min; date started: 2019-11-11; date completed: 2019-11-11

[[User:Zhi Wei Zeng|Zhi Wei Zeng]] ([[User talk:Zhi Wei Zeng|talk]]) 17:43, 11 November 2019 (EST)
</div>

;Experiment:
1. Microarrays: Detect mRNA levels by probes on a chip

2. RNA Sequencing: More direct and more prevalent nowadays. Align fragments to reference genome. However, converting reads of mRNA fragments to counts require "stochastic weighting".
: In addition, alignment to the reference genome should be "splice-aware" 

;Types of data files/formats:
:* SAM (sequence alignment map) & BAM (binary SAM) files: mapping of reads to the genome
:* BED files: specifies regions of interest in SAM/BAM. Extensive annotation and subsetting.

;Conversion of reads to counts:
e.g. RPKM, FPKM

;Expression databases:
:* GEO (NCBI): microarray and RNA-seq expression data
:* Expression Atlas (EMBL-EBI)

;Key questions:
Expressions and differential expressions of genes

{{Vspace}}
