;Step 1 - Target Sequence

1. Fetch the APSES doamin sequence for MBP1_ERECY. [http://steipe.biochemistry.utoronto.ca/abc/students/index.php/User:Zhi_Wei_Zeng/Journal#5.9.1_Construct_homology_model_for_ERECY_Mbp1 I have already done this in my journal]

2. The sequence is:
 "QIYSAKYSGVEVYEFIHPTGSIMKRKADDWVNATHILKAAKFAKAKRTRILEKEVIKDIHEKVQGGFGKYQGTWVPLDIARRLAEKFDVLEELRPLFDF"

;Step 2 - Template Structure and create alignment

3. From my past activity, I already had the sequence corresponding to PDB 4UX5 stored in "4UX5_A.fa".

4. Use the R-code provided [http://steipe.biochemistry.utoronto.ca/abc/index.php/BIN-SX-Homology_modelling#The_input_alignment here] by Dr. Steipe in RStudio with ABC-units project loaded.

Until the line where we are able to inspect the MSA or write to file.

'''Now, I choose 4UX5 as the template. I have to write the alignment to a different file.'''

I may not be able to re-use my old "APSES-MBP1.fa" because <code>fetchMSAmotif(MBP1msa, seq1BM8)</code> would only make sure to cover the sequence for 1BM8 but not necessarily 4UX5.

I follow the following R-code, which really is just a modified version of the code provided to me:

<source lang="R">
# Be careful to not overwrite, though I do have version control..
# My version control is in the directory parent to getwd()
writeMFA(fetchMSAmotif(MBP1msa, seq4UX5), myCon = "../APSES-MBP1_ALT.fa")

myT <- seq4UX5

# Everything below is the same as source code
# The code below has dependency on the variable targetName which I have not defined
# Define it with the following line
(targetName <- sprintf("MBP1_%s", biCode(MYSPE)))

targetSeq   <- as.character(fetchMSAmotif(MBP1msa, myT)[targetName])
templateSeq <- as.character(fetchMSAmotif(MBP1msa, myT)[names(myT)])
 
# Drop positions in which both sequences have hyphens.
targetSeq   <- unlist(strsplit(targetSeq,   ""))
templateSeq <- unlist(strsplit(templateSeq, ""))
gapMask <- ! ((targetSeq == "-") & (templateSeq == "-"))
targetSeq   <- paste0(targetSeq[gapMask], collapse = "")
templateSeq <- paste0(templateSeq[gapMask], collapse = "")
 
# Assemble sequences into a set
TTset <- character()
TTset[1] <- targetSeq
TTset[2] <- templateSeq
names(TTset) <- c(targetName, names(myT))
 
writeMFA(TTset)

</code>

Inspect the MSA result from file "APSES-MBP1_ALT.fa" in JalView:

[[File:jalview_ERECY.jpg]]

I have doubts about multiple sequence alignment in common residues 1-15 and 118-142.

At only a threshold of 20% conservation threshold, these regions still do not have strong colour indication for conservation.

Residues 121-132 looks pretty well aligned though. However, it is not clear how indels at 118-121 should be resolved.

So I decide to remove 1-15 and 118-142 from alignment for modelling (121-132 is honestly hard to let go..).

The resulting alignment stored in "hm_alt.mfa" is the following:

 >MBP1_ERECY
 QIYSAKYSGVEVYEFIHP-TGSIMKRKADDWVNATHILKAAKFAKAKRTRILEKEVIKDIHEKVQ
 GGFGKYQGTWVPLDIARRLAEKFDVLEELRPLFDF

 >4UX5_A
 GIYSATYSGIPVYEYQFGLKEHVMRRRVDDWINATHILKAAGFDKPARTRILEREVQKDQHEKVQ
 GGYGKYQGTWIPLEAGEALAHRNNIFDRLRPIFEF

;Step 3 - Build the model and process PDB

5. Use the above alignment to model at SWISS-MODEL at https://swissmodel.expasy.org/interactive#alignment

Job report at https://swissmodel.expasy.org/interactive/8aB2RD/models/

One indel is near the end of a beta-turn, resulting in more uncertainty there locally.

 Statistics: GMQE 0.78, QMEAN -0.47 (good)

6. Download the resulting PDB as "MBP1_ERECY-APSES_alt.pdb".

7. Use the modified source code [http://steipe.biochemistry.utoronto.ca/abc/index.php/BIN-SX-Homology_modelling#Renumbering_the_model here] to renumber the residues of the model correctly.

Modified code here:
<code>
if (! requireNamespace("bio3d", quietly=TRUE)) {
  install.packages("bio3d")
}
# Package information:
#  library(help = bio3d)       # basic information
#  browseVignettes("bio3d")    # available vignettes
#  data(package = "bio3d")     # available datasets

# Save with a different name
PDB_INFILE      <- "../MBP1_ERECY-APSES_alt.pdb" 
PDB_OUTFILE     <- "../MBP1_ERECY-APSESrenum_alt.pdb"
 
# residue number for the first residue if your template was 4UX5
# should actually be 16 though.
# The first residue aligned to the first residue in the homology model is not 14, due to me editing the multiple sequence alignment
iFirst <- 16  
 
# == Read the MYSPE pdb file
MYSPEmodel <- bio3d::read.pdb(PDB_INFILE) # read the PDB file into a list
 
MYSPEmodel           # examine the information
MYSPEmodel$atom[1,]  # get information for the first atom
 
# Explore ?bio3d::read.pdb and study the examples.
 
# == Modify residue numbers for each atom
resNum <- as.numeric(MYSPEmodel$atom[,"resno"])
resNum
resNum <- resNum - resNum[1] + iFirst  # add offset
MYSPEmodel$atom[ , "resno"] <- resNum   # replace old numbers with new
 
# check result
MYSPEmodel$atom[ , "resno"]
MYSPEmodel$atom[1, ]
 
# == Write output to file
bio3d::write.pdb(pdb = MYSPEmodel, file=PDB_OUTFILE) # An error from the code corrected here
</code>

Now, the numbering corresponds correctly to 4UX5 numbering.

;Step 4 - Visualization and superposition

8. In chimera, open 4ux5. Then, load the homology model I just made.

9. The homology model is already aligned to chain A of 4UX5 pretty well. But still, use "MatchMaker" to align it to chain A of 4UX5.

Hide ribbons for chain B of 4UX5.

10. Select chain A of my homology model. Change selection mode to "intersect" and then select positively charged residues. Show Atoms/Aonds for them.

11. Change selection mode back to "replace". Select chain C of 4UX5, which selects the strand of DNA that appears to contact the protein the most. Hide ribbons and show Atoms/Bonds

12. Somehow some water oxygens show up. Clear selection and then select Structure > Solvent. Hide Atoms/Bonds.

It now becomes a lot more apparent which positively charged sidechains are in close proximity to the phosphate backbone now.

13. Use command line to select residues and guide the decision of which DNA-contacting residues to display.

The selection command for all desired residues is <code>select #1:53.A,59.A,62.A,77.A,84.A</code>

;Step 5 - Choose conserved positively charged residues that contact DNA

14. Use Tools > Sequence > Multialign Viewer and open "hm_alt.mfa". File type is aligned FASTA.

Confirmed that all selected residues above are conserved between these two species.

15. Check with the JalView MSA I produced above.

<span style="color:red">I found out from inspecting the alignments that the renumbering code still did not renumber the residues correctly due to an indel in the alignment between template and target</span>

'''Making a script right now to address this very specific issue would be a nightmare, so I might as well manually correct them..'''

 The correct residue numbers corresponding to 4UX5 of my selected residues should actually be K56, K62, R65, K80, K87.
 As seen from the Multialign Viewer.

All of these residues are completely conserved except K87, which is an arginine in MBP1_NEUCR (still very well conserved in terms of positive charge).

Render with these residues

=References=
<references />

{{CC-BY}}
[[Category:EVAL-BIN-SX-Small_molecules]]