The following content is submitted for credit for the learning unit '''[http://steipe.biochemistry.utoronto.ca/abc/index.php/BIN-SX-Small_molecules BIN-SX-Small_molecules]'''

;The small molecule is progesterone.

;Summary:
'''Progesterone''' is a steroid hormone<ref name="wiki">Progesterone. (n.d.). In ''Wikipedia''. Retrieved December 2, 2019, from https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Progesterone</ref>. It functions by affecting cellular signal transduction.

Progesterone binds to the protein progesterone receptor. This results in a cascade of downstream effects, leading to changes in the expression of various genes<ref name="pubchem">PubChem Identifier: CID 5994. Retrieved December 2, 2019, from https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/compound/5994</ref>.

Progesterone inhibits estrogen by decreasing the expression of estrogen receptors as well as increasing the metabolism of estrogens<ref name="pubchem" />.

Progesterone is often known to be involved in female reproductive physiology (i.e. the menstrual cycle)<ref name="wiki" /><ref name="pubchem" />.

;Chemical Structure:

[[File:progesterone_cs.jpg|300px]]

(Generated by ChemDraw)

;SMILE String:
<code>CC(=O)[C@H]1CC[C@@H]2[C@@]1(CC[C@H]3[C@H]2CCC4=CC(=O)CC[C@]34C)C</code>

 Note:
 PubChem also gave another SMILE String as canonical SMILE string as the following
 <code>CC(=O)C1CCC2C1(CCC3C2CCC4=CC(=O)CCC34C)C</code>
 But this one is incorrect.
 It has the wrong stereochemistry for many hydrogens and methyls (by correct, I mean consistent with the 2D structure they provided).

(Obtained from PubChem)

;3D Structure:
[[File:progesterone_3d.jpg|300px]]

(This is now Model 1)

Using PDB "Search" > "Ligands", I found this struture with the SMILE string:

'''"HORMONE-BOUND HUMAN PROGESTERONE RECEPTOR LIGAND-BINDING DOMAIN" (PDB 1A28)'''

;Superposition:
To superimpose, the following command is used:
<code>match #0:1.A@C21,C20,O20,C17,C16,C15,C14,C13,C12,C11,C9,C8,C7,C6,C5,C4,C3,O3,C2,C1,C10,C19,C18 #1@C1,C2,O1,C3,C4,C5,C6,C7,C8,C9,C10,C11,C12,C13,C14,C15,C16,O2,C17,C18,C19,C20,C21</code>

[[File:prog_sup.jpg|500px]]

It looks like the superposition at the acyl tail is the worst, which may reduce the quality of the superposition of rigid tetra-ring system.

So I instead removed the acyl atoms from superposition:
<code>match #0:1.A@C17,C16,C15,C14,C13,C12,C11,C9,C8,C7,C6,C5,C4,C3,O3,C2,C1,C10,C19,C18 #1@C3,C4,C5,C6,C7,C8,C9,C10,C11,C12,C13,C14,C15,C16,O2,C17,C18,C19,C20,C21</code>

... which resulted in much better alignment of the rigid rings.

It is apparent that the superposition is quite good. The greatest deviation occurs at the acetyl tail.

Perhaps due to a slightly different conformation of the five-membered ring and the acyl tail, the methyl attached to the five-membered ring also seems to noticeably deviate from my structural model.

;Stereo Image:

[[File:prog_sup_stereo.jpg|600px]]

=References=
<references />

{{CC-BY}}
[[Category:EVAL-BIN-SX-Small_molecules]]